okay we're gonna meditate
relax face little smile I eyelids are
relaxed fingers are relaxed the
shoulders are relaxed Papa a little bit
stomach is always slightly tight not not
too much just slight tension try to
relax your forehead
and we'll start watching our breath long
exhales after the lungs are finished
exhaling exhale it'll bit more when the
lungs pause before the inhale exhale
just a little bit more it's really
really important for not building up
prana Chi then getting nervous from your
meditation
let's go through the SAP Jeong
collecting good sales for this
meditation and removing bad seats for
this meditation but we'll do it a little
quickly some mornings you'll be too busy
you won't have enough time to do it but
if you do have time it's good so ask one
of your teachers to come maybe you'll
stay with the same teacher for a few
days or a few weeks or forever if it's
your heart teacher or maybe you mix it
up and you try different teacher each
day if you try a different teacher each
day it's kind of nice because you might
find teachers that you didn't remember
or you didn't recognize especially
people who hurt you in your life so
choose a teacher and ask them to come
and sit with you
think of something you admire about your
positive teachers and this is a mental
prostration something you would like to
learn or be yourself
then make an offering especially if some
improvement you've made in yourself in
the last few days especially
didn't tell your teacher about some
mistake you've made in the last few days
something you're not proud of and some
something you did which was not very
nice
then ask for teachings today could be
Dharma teachings could be problems that
show you more about yourself
and ask a teacher to stay with you
this week we're going to do different
meditations about the six triggers six
things which trigger negative emotion
yes mine and we'll do different
meditations about the six triggers and
the tool that we'll use his caution you
know decision it's the smoke alarm the
state of mind that we use during
meditation it checks to see if you're
thinking about something else or maybe
you're spacing out and you're just not
thinking about anything and then shishun
is watching the mind
Shane is checking the quality of the
meditation and then Shane helps set off
an alarm for Temba which brings the mind
back to meditation so this morning we're
gonna use shaken watcher watcher of the
mind to just observe the morning State
of Mind
most people in the morning their state
of mind is pretty smooth just like the
ocean in the morning the temperature of
the ocean and the lab is about the same
there's not much wind
so observe your mind how smooth is it
this morning how gentle quiet were not
tired yet we haven't had a moderate
it's happened yet this morning today the
mind is still pretty fresh pretty open
pretty relaxed
so use your shaking to just appreciate
the morning State of Mind morning is a
good time for most people to do things
that require a lot of thought or
planning so just enjoy your mind look at
your mind like glassy quiet water
you know I'd like you to disturb this
water purposely let's recreate a
negative emotion that's caused ecclesia
and then that's watch with rescission
what happens to the come water of the
mind so I'd like you to think about
somebody that you're having a problem
with in the last few days a week or
month okay so usually it's not very
pleasant to think about someone who's
causing us trouble but bring them to
mind purposely and then use your session
to see what happens with the water it's
very subtle and meditation is a good
time to watch usually during the day
things are going too fast for us to
watch what's happening in our mind when
we meet this person so let's practice in
the morning meditation meeting this
person was giving us a trouble
maybe they reach out to us or they text
us or we see them directing or we think
about them strongly so on purpose let's
shake up the nice peaceful water of the
mind by purposely thinking about someone
who's giving us trouble nowadays and
let's see how it feels
how how does the mind feel and we're
gonna practice this a few times with
different objects and
the goal is to learn to feel detect with
your smoke alarm concession that your
mind is getting off balance and perhaps
you could start to get angry or how
desire so here we go unpleasant
meditation bring someone in the mind
who's giving you a little bit of trouble
nowadays remember we're meditating in a
group so try not to move
try not to make noise
now please try to come back to the
carmine we saw how it feels to shake up
the water and let's smooth the water out
again try not to think about the person
send them away from your thoughts if
your thoughts start to come back to this
person then just gently think about
something else
come back to the quiet mind try to send
that object away from your thoughts and
come back to this morning clear mine
soft mine
in the last few months we've been
traveling and sharing DCI with people in
different countries and we've taught
level six a lot which is about getting
rid of your addictions then when you
talk about addictions usually you think
about cigarettes or alcohol drugs things
like cellphone things like this but and
you think about addictions then and
something that other people have like oh
my uncle is an alcoholic or my friend is
addicted to cigarettes but long rim says
that we're all addicted we all have
addictions some of them are legal some
of them are not
sometimes the illegal addictions become
legal addictions some addictions are
obvious to other people and some
addictions are private but they all have
one quality and that's they they disturb
your mind so if I'm in the prayer last
night and I'm addicted to cookies then
when I eat the cookies I I don't feel
like sharing them I want them all for
myself
and I eat too many and I can't stop
so addictions hurt myself and they hurt
other people it's different from
enjoying a cookie so there are some
people in this room who don't have
cookie addiction like geshe michael has
they can eat one cookie at the lama
chuppah
and they feel happy and that's enough
and their mind is soft and glassy smooth
it's not disturbed
geshe michael when he eats a cookie his
mind starts to get disturbed so I'd like
you to think about something you might
be addicted to for me maybe it's cookies
but the lar mem says all of us have some
addiction so think about what am i
addicted to it means I can't stop
wanting it I I might hurt or
inconvenience other people to get it and
I wouldn't want to share it so think
about one thing that you're addicted to
it could also be emotional addiction I I
like people to praise me I get upset if
they don't praise me things like that
okay go ahead we're not gonna meditate
much longer maybe five more minutes
and I'd like you to bring that object to
mind let's see what it does to the soft
smooth mind when you think strongly
about the thing you're addicted to so
before we were purposely disturbing the
mind by thinking about someone we don't
like now we're going to think about the
thing we might be addicted to and I'd
like you to watch the mind the peace of
mind
the smooth mind and see if the mind gets
stirred up agitated and I'd like you to
compare that agitated mind to the one we
had before with the angry person or the
person we don't like is the agitated
mind the same or is it somehow different
okay so if you bring to mind somebody
you're having a problem with or you
bring to mind cookies or something you
have an addiction to is the effect on
the mind the same does the mind get
stirred up exactly the same or is it a
little bit different okay let's do this
for about two minutes three minutes and
then we'll stop and then I'd like to
hear from some of you is this third up
mind the same or is this somehow
different
and please take three deep exhales don't
open your eyes yet you can use those
last three excels as a opportunity to do
the last meditation preliminary which is
to give away the good karma of your
meditation to other people
and then slowly open your eyes take a
stretch
[Music]
drink some drink something if you have
okay you're in the desert and you have
to keep drinking okay
if you want to get something to drink
you're welcome to
I'd like to hear from people about that
question and then we'll take a break
after that okay we'll take a pee-pee
break after that that's also disturbed
water so what's the difference okay
did you find a difference you know the -
morning - smooth kind of gentle and then
we thought about somebody we're having a
problem with and we watched it with our
what shaking and we saw the water start
to go like this you know then we tried
to bring the water back to normal and
then we brought in the cookie or the
object of your addiction whatever's here
at diction it could be an emotional
addiction addiction and then the water
got stirred up again and my question to
you is and what I'd like to hear from
people is there a difference between
those two stirred up waters and Yelena's
gonna start I think okay
cool anybody else let's do five or six
people
yeah I like it yeah I like anybody else
Regina
wait say again I I couldn't you can you
turn it up a little bit yeah okay okay
[Laughter]
Pasha Pasha behind you
cool anyone else
yeah anybody else I'm curious I'm
curious if the shaky water is the same
it's the disturbance of the mind equal
or not but your own your own answer
[Music]
you failed in the meditation
okay anyone else want to share
don't be shy
cool one more two more
dreamer
cellphones
yeah
okay hot so head look our first house or
second okay ladies first
okay tight yeah okay
yeah the breath changes yeah yeah yeah
yeah okay
yeah meditation
so
yeah
okay cool cool anybody else really
wanted thank you okay
we're gonna take a break but I'll leave
you with one thought okay and the alarm
room then we're gonna do the alarm room
and it's gonna talk about it so are
those two shaky water mines are they
both equally maybe gonna cause you to
hurt someone okay to do something to
somebody off okay are they equal it's
the irritated mind and shaky I want more
cookies mine
are they equal that maybe in the next
five minutes you will hurt somebody you
will say something to somebody or you
will do something to somebody okay
think about that during your pee pee
break
and when you get back tell me what you
think okay all right